Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.16
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Articles and Op-Eds, 1956-2013; XVI.
  - Articles, 1956-2017; 1.
    - New Material Added, April 2020
      - "The Credit Crisis and Corporate Failures" Executive Counsel, November-December 2008 (Box 1071, Folder 72)
      - Brief re: US Court of Appeals, Livnat, et al v. Aalestinian Authority, July 2015 (Box 1071, Folder 73)
      - Foreword: Howard Hills book, re: Puerto Rico, September 2015 (Box 1071, Folder 74)
      - Thornburgh Expert Witness Statement re: Nicolas Leoz Indictment filed c. May 20, 2015, November 30, 2015 (Box 1071, Folder 75)
      - Update, re: "Citizens Without a State"; No. 15-3135 US Court of Appeals, Second Circuit, Brief, December 15, 2015 (Box 1071, Folder 76)
      - "Disability and the Prophet's Call" The Christian Citizen, July 26, 2017 (Box 1071, Folder 77)
  - Op-Eds, 1964-2018; 2.
    - "GOP Moderates Must Rebuild Party," (Pittsburgh Post-Gazette) and other Op-Eds, November 6, 1964 (Box 983, Folder 1)
    - "Thornburgh Discusses Five Important Issues," Republican Voice, August, 1966 (Box 983, Folder 2)
    - Time is Ripe for Peace Talks, Letter to the Editor, Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, December 7, 1967 (Box 983, Folder 3)
    - "How to Support Your Local Police," Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, December 8, 1972 (Box 983, Folder 4)
    - "I Regard Unauthorized Wiretap as Serious Threat," Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, June, 1973 (Box 983, Folder 5)
    - "How to Support Your Local Police," Pittsburgh Press, June 4, 1973 (Box 983, Folder 6)
    - "Who 'Owns' Public Officials?" Pittsburgh Press, February 22, 1974 (Box 983, Folder 7)
    - "One Nation, Under God…" Pittsburgh Press, June 29, 1975 (Box 983, Folder 8)
    - "For the Record," Speech excerpt regarding white collar crime, Washington Post, February 12, 1976 (Box 983, Folder 9)
    - "Thornburgh Defends Senate Crime Code Revisions," Pittsburgh Press, March 13, 1976 (Box 983, Folder 10)
    - "The Changes in S.1," Washington Post, May 6, 1976 (Box 983, Folder 11)
    - "Of S.1 and the First Amendment," Letter to Editor, New York Times, June 11, 1976 (Box 983, Folder 12)
    - "Start to Fight White Collar Crime," Philadelphia Inquirer, April 5, 1977 (Box 983, Folder 13)
    - "After Three Mile Island," New York Times, March 27, 1980 (Box 983, Folder 14)
    - "Easing Public Fers in the Wake of TMI," Letter to the Editor, New York Times, May 27, 1980 (Box 983, Folder 15)
    - Welfare Cuts in Line with the Economic Realities," Philadelphia Inquirer, June 9, 1980 (Box 983, Folder 16)
    - "Welfare Could Collapse of its own Weight," Philadelphia Inquirer, June 22, 1980 (Box 983, Folder 17)
    - "Complaints Ignored Too Long," Philadelphia Bulletin, February 4, 1981 (Box 983, Folder 18)
    - "Step-wise to Decontrol," Philadelphia Daily News, February 18, 1981 (Box 983, Folder 19)
    - "State Gains Defended," New York Times, May 3, 1981 (Box 983, Folder 20)
    - "Selecting Judges by Merit," York Daily Record, May 27, 1981 (Box 983, Folder 21)
    - "There is not TMI Choice: Resolving Safety, Funding Comes First," NRC Testimony, Philadelphia Inquirer, August 19, 1981 (Box 983, Folder 22)
    - "Health Care Help for the Unemployed," Letter to the Editor, Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, June 1, 1983 (Box 983, Folder 23)
    - "The State is Pushing for Excellence in School," Philadelphia Inquirer, November 23, 1983 (Box 983, Folder 24)
    - "Education Reforms Needed in State," Harrisburg Evening News, November 23, 1983 (Box 983, Folder 25)
    - "An American 'cabbage patch' thrives in Communist China," Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, January 18, 1984 (Box 983, Folder 26)
    - "Why a Balanced Budget Amendment - - the 'Politics as Usual' that Puts Us in the Hole Opposes Reform," Los Angeles Times, February 1, 1985 (Box 983, Folder 27)
    - "Case for a Balanced Budget Amendment," Letter to the Editor, New York Times, March 13, 1985 (Box 983, Folder 28)
    - "The Year to End the State Stores," Philadelphia Inquirer, April 3, 1985 (Box 983, Folder 29)
    - "Dedicated to Improving Public Education in Pennsylvania," Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, September 17, 1985 (Box 983, Folder 30)
    - "Governors respond to the deficit dilemma," Harrisburg Patiot News, October 6, 1985 (Box 983, Folder 31)
    - "Balanced Budgets: Good for the Country," Letter to the Editor, Washington Post, May 4, 1986 (Box 983, Folder 32)
    - "State's Welfare Reform is Working," Philadelphia Inquirer, March 19, 1986 (Box 983, Folder 33)
    - "How We Tried to Tell the Russians About TMI," Washington Post, May 4, 1986 (Box 983, Folder 34)
    - "Secrecy Threatens Another Chernobyl," Pittsburgh Press, May 6, 1986 (Box 983, Folder 35)
    - "Lesson TMI Lost on Soviets," Harrisburg Patriot, May 7, 1986 (Box 983, Folder 36)
    - "The Judges Should be Selected on Merit," Philadelphia Inquirer, April 12, 1987 (Box 983, Folder 37)
    - "America Needs Amendment on Balanced Budget," Toledo Blade, January 3, 1988 (Box 983, Folder 38)
    - "A System Without Merit," Point of View Column, Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, March 26, 1988 (Box 983, Folder 39)
    - "States Can Teach Washington Deficits," Letter to the Editor, New York Times, July 14, 1988 (Box 983, Folder 40)
    - "Antitrust Exemptions to Spur Ventures," Wall Street Journal, December 27, 1988 (Box 983, Folder 41)
    - "More Refugees? It's Up to Congress," Letter to the Editor, Washington Post, October 1, 1989 (Box 983, Folder 42)
    - "Potomac Politics on Kapital Hill," New York Times, November 7, 1989 (Box 983, Folder 43)
    - "Thornburgh in Kremlin," Philadelphia Daily News, November 9, 1989 (Box 983, Folder 44)
    - "Worldwide Alliance Against Drugs," The Christian Science Monitor, March 1, 1990 (Box 983, Folder 45)
    - "U.S. Government is Going After the Savings and Loans Cheats," Philadelphia Inquirer, September 2, 1990 (Box 983, Folder 46)
    - "The House Crime Bill': Attorney General Thornburgh Responds," Washington Post, September 23, 1990 (Box 983, Folder 47)
    - "One Anti-Crime Bill, One Pro-Crime Bill," Wall Street Journal, September 26, 1990 (Box 983, Folder 48)
    - "Curbing Death Row Appeals," USA Today, October 5, 1990 (Box 983, Folder 49)
    - "Now Reverse the Trend of Nullifying the Death Penalty," New York Times, October 18, 1990 (Box 983, Folder 50)
    - "Sumer of '41," Book Review of Real Grass Real Heroes by Dom Dimaggio with Bill Gilbert, Washington Post, October 21, 1990 (Box 983, Folder 51)
    - "The Cream of Coffeetable Books," Book Review of Topps Baseball Cards, New York Times, December 2, 1990 (Box 983, Folder 52)
    - "Six Real Guns …," Washington Post, May 2, 1991 (Box 983, Folder 53)
    - "Tracing 6 Real Guns and How They Killed," Philadelphia Inquirer, May 4, 1991 (Box 983, Folder 54)
    - "There's a Way Out of the Deficit: It's a Balanced Budget Amendment," Philadelphia Inquirer, February 12, 1992 (Box 983, Folder 55)
    - "Time for US to Adopt Balanced-Budget Law," Christian Science Monitor, March 18, 1993 (Box 983, Folder 56)
    - "To Make the U.N. Work," Washington Post, March 25, 1993 (Box 983, Folder 57)
    - "How to Clean Up the United Nations," International Herald Tribune, March 26, 1993 (Box 983, Folder 58)
    - "Take an Old Classic for a Satisfying Spin," USA Today Baseball Weekly, October 13, 1993 (Box 983, Folder 59)
    - "How Russia Can Make its Next Elections Fairer," Washington Times, December 27, 1993 (Box 983, Folder 60)
    - "Bring Back the Czar," Wall Street Journal, August 29, 1994 (Box 983, Folder 61)
    - "America's Civil Justice Lottery," San Francisco Chronicle, May 9, 1995 (Box 983, Folder 62)
    - "ADA - - Not a Disabling Mandate," by Janet Reno and Dick Thornburgh, Wall Street Journal, July 26, 1995 (Box 983, Folder 63)
    - "A Blow to Hong Kong's Future," Washington Post, July 30, 1995 (Box 983, Folder 64)
    - "Huge Damages Turn Justice on Its Head," Los Angeles Times, December 5, 1995 (Box 983, Folder 65)
    - "Few, Other than Lawyers, Benefit from Civil Justice," San Diego Union-Tribune, December 6, 1995 (Box 983, Folder 66)
    - "Expand States' Role in New R&D Policy," Boston Globe, January 2, 1996 (Box 983, Folder 67)
    - "Don't Let Litigation Kill Medical Miracles," Washington Times, April 23, 1996 (Box 983, Folder 68)
    - "Out of Balance, Still," Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, June 11, 1996 (Box 983, Folder 69)
    - "A Democratic Process Takes Shape in Russia," Philadelphia Inquirer, June 24, 1996 (Box 983, Folder 70)
    - "Want to Win a Big Suit? Go to Alabama," USA Today, June 27, 1996 (Box 983, Folder 71)
    - "'Tort Hell': Outlandish GM Case Solidifies Alabama's Reputation," Montgomery Advisor, August 1, 1996 (Box 983, Folder 72)
    - "U.S. Must Hold China to Hong Kong Pledge," New York Times (includes correction), October 23, 1996 (October 29, 1996) (Box 983, Folder 73)
    - "New Chief Must Tackle U.N. Reform," Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, December 29, 1996 (Box 983, Folder 74)
    - "Don't Muzzle Judicial Critics," St. Louis Post-Dispatch, February 5, 1997 (Box 983, Folder 75)
    - "Frivolous Lawsuitt Safeguards Under Attack," Detroit News, July 20, 1997 (Box 983, Folder 76)
    - "Enough of Class-Action Abuse," Washington Times, October 30, 1997 (Box 983, Folder 77)
    - "Sending Europe a Bad Message," New York Times, February 15, 1998 (Box 983, Folder 78)
    - "Lawsuit Abuse," Washington Post, April 1, 1998 (Box 983, Folder 79)
    - "A New Judicial Imperialism," Wall Street Journal, May 18, 1998 (Box 983, Folder 80)
    - "Facts on U.S. Nationality and Citizenship," San Juan Star, June 1, 1998 (Box 983, Folder 81)
    - "Perjury is Perjury," Wall Street Journal, September 22, 1998 (Box 983, Folder 82)
    - "Defining Moment for Puerto Rico," Washington Post, November 19, 1998 (Box 983, Folder 83)
    - "The Law Liberals Finally Learned to Hate," Wall Street Journal, February 24, 1999 (Box 983, Folder 84)
    - "Lessons from TMI," Harrisburg Patriot-News, March 28, 1999 (Box 983, Folder 85)
    - "FTC Seeks Precedent Only a Trial Lawyer Could Love," Wall Street Journal, May 10, 1999 (Box 983, Folder 86)
    - "Federalist Society Hardly Qualifies as a Fifth Column," Detroit News, June 30, 1999 (Box 983, Folder 87)
    - "Trying times for trial lawyers," Palm Beach Post, July 22, 1999 (Box 983, Folder 88)
    - "Prosecutors and State Ethical Rules: Trying a Commonsense Approach," Tribune-Review, September 9, 1999 (Box 983, Folder 89)
    - "Trial Lawyer, Heal Thyself: Bring Sanity to Punitive Damage Awards," Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, September 29, 1999 (Box 983, Folder 90)
    - "Zap Some Lawyers: Go for Arbitration," USA Today, October 7, 1999 (Box 983, Folder 91)
    - "Puerto Rico Statehood Would Best Serve the Nation's Interests," Union Leader, Manchester, NH, November 30, 1999 (Box 983, Folder 92)
    - "No End in Sight as Punitive Damages Go Up, Up, Up," Wall Street Journal, March 13, 2000 (Box 983, Folder 93)
    - "The HMO Dilemma: What's the Fairest Battlefield in the Fight for Better Health Care?", Los Angeles Times, April 23, 2000 (Box 983, Folder 94)
    - "Sue, but Don't Prosecute," New York Times, September 20, 2000 (Box 983, Folder 95)
    - "The Supreme Court Can End the Charade," Wall Street Journal, November 30, 2000 (Box 983, Folder 96)
    - "Of Pardons and Plea Bargains," Wall Street Journal, January 24, 2001 (Box 983, Folder 97)
    - "Court Ruling Bolsters State Lead Paint Suit," Letter to Editor, San Fransicsco Chronicle, April 8, 2001 (Box 983, Folder 98)
    - "The Right Man for a Tough Job," Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, July 15, 2001 (Box 983, Folder 99)
    - "High Times in Sequoyah County," The Oklahoman, August 29, 2001 (Box 983, Folder 100)
    - "The Northwest Ordinance: No precedent," San Juan Star, October 11, 2001 (Box 983, Folder 101)
    - "Just Say No to Tort Blackmail," Wall Street Journal, January 21, 2002 (Box 983, Folder 102)
    - "Setting the Record Straight on Judge D. Brooks Smith," Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, February 26, 2002 (Box 983, Folder 103)
    - "Judgment Call in the Senate," Letter to Editor re Judge Smith, Washington Post, March 9, 2002 (Box 983, Folder 104)
    - "The legal realities of U.S. citizenship in Puerto Rico," San Juan Star, April 8, 2002 (Box 983, Folder 105)
    - "Well Before Sept. 11, Congress Overtaxed the F.B.I.," New York Times, June 29, 2002 (Box 983, Folder 106)
    - "Bravery inspires first Fourth of July since Sept. 11 tragedy," Harrisburg Patroit-News, July 4, 2002 (Box 983, Folder 107)
    - "Asbestos litigation has gone out of control," Harrisburg Patriot-News, November 22, 2002 (Box 983, Folder 108)
    - "Two Lawyers Say: Limit Damages, Fees," Philadelphia Inquirer, January 8, 2003 (Box 983, Folder 109)
    - "Hong Kong's Struggle", June 13, 2003 (Box 983, Folder 110)
    - "Do the Right Thing," Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, March 30, 2004 (Box 983, Folder 111)
    - "Let Starr do His Job, Wall Street Journal, March 11, 1998 (Box 983, Folder 112)
    - "Yes to county row office consolidation", Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, May 8, 2005 (Box 983, Folder 113)
    - "Response to 'The Flawed Report on Dan Rather'", New York Review of Books, Letter to Editor, May 12, 2005 (Box 983, Folder 114)
    - "Defending a Probe and a Principle", Washington Post, May 17, 2005 (Box 983, Folder 115)
    - "The Fantastic Five", New York Times, September 12, 2005 (Box 983, Folder 116)
    - "Trade pact stomps on lumber", Register-Guard, Eugene, Oregon, October 5, 2005 (Box 983, Folder 117)
    - "Doctors, Lawyers, Priests - and Journalists?, Wall Street Journal, July 3, 2006 (Box 983, Folder 118)
    - "Watch Out for Voting Day Bugs", Washington Post and many other newspapers, August 28, 2006 (Box 983, Folder 119)
    - "Puerto Rican Limbo", Wall Street Journal, April 23, 2007 (Box 983, Folder 120)
    - "Citizens Want Political Status Defined", S. Florida Sun-Sentinel, June 14, 2007 (Box 983, Folder 121)
    - "Class Action Gamesmanship", Washington Times, June 15, 2007 (Box 983, Folder 122)
    - "Sirius and XM", Washington Times, March 10, 2008 (Box 983, Folder 123)
    - "Creating a 'Greater Pittsburgh'", Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, April 13, 2008 (Box 983, Folder 124)
    - "Siriusly, FCC Should Put a Spike Through This", Wall Street Journal, June 19, 2008 (Box 983, Folder 125)
    - Opposing view: "Don't fix what ain't broke", USA Today, December 22, 2008 (Box 983, Folder 126)
    - "More Cops on the Street", New York Times, December 28, 2008 (Box 983, Folder 127)
    - "China's Harassed Lawyers", New York Times, July 28, 2009 (Box 983, Folder 128)
    - "Turnpike Commission must be Severed", Allentown Morning Call and others, December 20, 2009 (Box 983, Folder 129)
    - "Balanced Budget Amendment is not a Nutty Idea", Several papers different titles, July 21, 2011 (Box 983, Folder 130)
    - New Material Added, December 2014
      - "What is free about free association?" San Juan Star, October 20, 2002 (Box 1039, Folder 36)
      - "Internet Safety," Letter to Editor, New York Tmes, December 2, 2002 (Box 1039, Folder 37)
      - "The Private Sector," Post-Gazette, March 30, 2004 (Box 1039, Folder 38)
      - "Narrow decision jeopardizes access for disabled," Patriot-News, Harrisburg, by Thornburgh and Tom Harkin, June 20, 2004 (Box 1039, Folder 39)
      - "Dred Scott and Balzac - A legacy of equality denied," San Juan Star, July 14, 2004 (Box 1039, Folder 40)
      - " Human Rights for the Disabled," Washington Post, by Thornburgh and Alan Reich, November 3, 2004 (Box 1039, Folder 41)
      - "Surveillance Sanity," Wall Street Journal, by Thornburgh and Benjamin Civiletti and William Webster, October 31, 2007 (Box 1039, Folder 42)
      - "U.S. reluctance to sign treaty on disabilities is painful, puzzling," Seattle Times, by Thornburgh and Paul Steven Miller, June 25, 2008 (Box 1039, Folder 43)
      - "Freeh hastily misjudged Paterno," USA Today, February 11, 2013 (Box 1039, Folder 44)
    - New Material Added, May 2017
      - "Junk Science Makes Junk Law, New York Times, February 10, 1997 (Box 1049, Folder 37)
      - "U.N. goals and reform depend upon American participation," Washington Times, October 28, 1999 (Box 1049, Folder 38)
      - "External review offers health-care aid," Sunday Patriot-News, April 16, 2000 (Box 1049, Folder 39)
      - "China's Harassed Lawyers," New York Times, July 28, 2009 (Box 1049, Folder 40)
      - "Ratify Convention to Break Down Global Barriers for the Disabled," Philly.com, December 1, 2013 (Box 1049, Folder 41)
      - "Penn State should release Freeh report documents, AP article, April 17, 2015 (Box 1049, Folder 42)
    - New Material Added, April 2020
      - "Dick Thornburgh: The disabilities revolution": Pittsburgh Post Gazette, May 3, 2015 (Box 1071, Folder 78)
      - "Commit to saving Chesapeake Bay" The Inquirer, July 20, 2015 (Box 1071, Folder 79)
      - "Ensuring justice for all", Pittsburgh Post Gazette, March 5, 2017 (Box 1071, Folder 80)
      - "Former U.S. AG: President Trump, please don't cut Legal Services", June 15, 2017 (Box 1071, Folder 81)
      - "We Republicans must all speak out to protect the Mueller investigation" Washington Post, June 8, 2018 (Box 1071, Folder 82)
      - "Robert Mueller will defend the rule of a law. Republicans should, too. Special to Washington Post, published in The Inquirer, Philly daily news, June 17, 2018 (Box 1071, Folder 83)
      - "Message: 300th Anniversary of the death of Governor William Penn", September 30, 2018 (Box 1071, Folder 84)
      - Statement on death of George H.W. Bush, December 1, 2018 (Box 1071, Folder 85)